Register of the Elena Varneck Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Elena Varneck papers,
1930-1933
XX272
Varneck, Elena, 1891-1976
18 manuscript boxes (7.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Research notes, drafts of writings, and translations, relating to a proposed publication entitled Revolution and Civil War In Siberia and the Far East, pertaining to events of the Russian Revolution and Civil War in Siberia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1891 Born, Kiev, Russia
1917 Translator at the Russian Embassy in Washington, D.C., for the Provisional Government
1928-1929 Translator at the Harvard University Medical School
1929-1942 Research Associate at the Hoover Institution
1935 Editor of The Testimony of Kolchak and Other Siberian Materials, published by Stanford University Press
1942-1945 Translator at the U.S. Department of State and at the first United Nations Conference
1948-1951 Instructor of Russian language at Stanford University
1976 Died, Stanford, CA
Scope and Content Note
The Elena Varneck papers consist primarily of Elena Varneck's translations from Russian into English of published and unpublished materials. Much of the translations are from newspapers and serials. Various aspects of social conditions and events during the revolution and civil war in Siberia, 1917-1923, are made accessible in these translations. Some of these translations were used in Varneck's book The Testimony of Kolchak and Other Siberian Materials (1935).
In the writings series, E. Varneck's typescript autobiography details events and conditions in Russia prior to the 1917 Revolution. Included are various references to the educational system and military schools during that time. This series also reflects Varneck's own research and findings relating to the revolution and civil war in both Russia and Siberia.
There are also many translations on the same subject by E. Varneck of various manuscripts at the Hoover Institution Archives. These materials are cataloged by the name of author with an added entry under the name Elena Varneck. They are also accessible by using the appropriate subject heading in the card catalog.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1930-1933. (Box 1)
  Correspondence arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent
- Writings, 1930s. (Box 1-2)
  Undated autobiography, essays, notes, and report, arranged alphabetically by topic within an untitled category and then by title
- Translations and Excerpts from Various Published and Unpublished Sources, 1930s. (Box 2-18)
  Translations of articles, essays, memoirs, excerpts from books, and other materials, arranged alphabetically by topic within a general category and then by author. Includes notes relating to the translations
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1930-1933 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1930 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Gutman, Anatol, 1933 (Folder 1: 2)
  - Mansvetov, Fedor, 1931 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Puchkov, Fedor, 1930 (Folder 1: 4)
- WRITINGS, 1930s
  - Untitled typescripts with handwritten annotations, drafts, and notes
    - General (Folder 1: 5)
    - Biographical information on various diplomats, military personnel, and statesmen, n.d. (Folder 1: 6)
    - Russian Imperial Family, Murder of, 1918 (Folder 1: 7)
    - Siberia - History
      - General (Folder 1: 8)
      - Revolution, 1917-1923
        - General (Folder 1: 9-10)
        - Chronologies (Folder 1: 11)
        - Kolchak government (Folder 1: 12)
  - "Attempts to Create an All-Russian Government," n.d. (Folder 1: 13)
    Typescript
  - Autobiography, n.d. (Folder 1: 14)
    Typescript with handwritten annotations
  - Autobiography, n.d. (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
  - "Bolshevik Revolution," n.d. (Folder 2: 4)
    Outline. Typescript
  - "The Government of Admiral Kolchak," n.d. (Folder 2: 5)
  - "Plan sbornika dokumentov i istoricheskikh materialov po revoliutsii, grazhdanskoi voiny i interventsii v Sibiri i na dal'nem vostoke," n.d. (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Report to the Provisional Government from the Commission for Investigating the Circumstances of Events of April 4-6, 1920, in Vladivostok," n.d. (Folder 2: 7)
- TRANSLATIONS AND EXCERPTS FROM VARIOUS PUBLISHED AND UNPUBLISHED SOURCES, 1930s.
  Primarily typescripts with handwritten annotations
  - General
    - General (Folder 2: 8)
    - Chernov Manifesto (Folder 2: 9)
  - Chinese Eastern Railway (Folder 2: 10)
    - Izhevsk (Russia) (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Russia. Posol'stvo (United States), selected documents (Folder 3: 2)
    - Samara government, 1918 (Folder 3: 3-6)
    - Siberia
      - Emigration (Folder 3: 7)
      - History
        - Pre-1917
          - General (Folder 3: 8)
          - Lena Massacre, 1912 (Folder 3: 9)
        - Revolution, 1905-1907 (Folder 3: 10)
        - Revolution, 1917-1923
          - General (Folder 4: 1-6)
          - General (Box-folder 5: 1-6)
          - General (Box-folder 6: 1-7)
          - General (Box-folder 7: 1-6)
          - General (Box-folder 8: 1-6)
          - General (Box-folder 9: 1-6)
          - General (Box-folder 10: 1-4)
          - Amur region
            - General (Folder 10: 5)
            - Blagoveshchensk (Folder 10: 6)
          - Ataman warriors (Folder 10: 7)
          - Chita (Folder 10: 8)
          - Cooperatives (Folder 10: 9)
          - Cossacks
            - General (Folder 10: 10)
            - Orenburg Cossacks (Folder 10: 11)
            - Ural Cossacks (Folder 10: 12)
          - Derber government (Folder 10: 13)
          - Directorate period and the Volga socialists (Box-folder 11: 1-2)
          - Early Soviet rule (Folder 11: 3-4)
          - Far East (Folder 11: 5-7)
          - Foreign intervention
            - General (Folder 11: 8-9)
            - Czechoslovakia (Box 12)
              - General (Folder 12: 1-6)
              - Czechoslovak troops (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
              - Mirbach intrigue (Folder 13: 3)
              - Stalin agreement (Folder 13: 4)
            - France (Folder 13: 5)
            - Great Britain (Folder 13: 6)
            - Hungary (Folder 13: 7)
            - Japan (Folder 13: 8-11)
            - Poland (Folder 13: 12)
            - United States
              - General (Folder 13: 13)
              - United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces (Folder 13: 14)
          - Gold reserve (Folder 14: 1)
          - Government Directorate (Folder 14: 2)
          - "Icy March" (Folder 14: 3)
          - Irkutsk (Folder 14: 4)
          - Kamchatka (Folder 14: 5)
          - Khabarovsk (Folder 14: 6)
          - Kolchak, Aleksandr V. (Folder 14: 7)
          - Kolchak government (Folder 14: 8-9)
          - Kolchak government (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
          - Mongolia (Folder 15: 3)
          - Nikolaevsk na Amure (Folder 15: 4)
          - Omsk (Folder 15: 5)
          - Overthrow of the government, 1918 November (Folder 15: 6-7)
          - Partisan war (Folder 15: 8)
          - Partisan war (Box-folder 16: 1-2)
          - Prinkipo proposal (Folder 16: 3)
          - Prisoners of war (Folder 16: 4)
          - Sakhalin (Folder 16: 5)
          - Secret White organizations (Folder 16: 6)
          - Semenov, Grigorii (Folder 16: 7)
          - Siberian Duma (Folder 16: 8)
          - Social Revolutionaries (Folder 16: 9)
          - Ufa (Folder 16: 10)
          - Vladivostok (Folder 16: 11-12)
          - Vladivostok (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
          - Voevodin (Folder 17: 3)
          - White armies (Folder 17: 4)
          - Yakutia (Folder 17: 5)
      - Nationalities (Folder 17: 6)
    - Ungern-Shternberg, Roman (Folder 17: 7)
    - Ural region (Folder 17: 8)
  - Andrushkevich, Nikolai A., various writings relating to Siberia, 1917-1923 (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - Efimov, A., "Expedition to the Suchan," Vestnik Veteranov, n.d. (Folder 18: 2)
  - Iaremenko, A. N., "Dnevnik Kommunista," Revoliutsiia na Dal'nem Vostoke, Moscow, 1923 (Folder 18: 3)